Guide to the California Rural Legal Assistance, Inc. records M0750
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
- Record Group 2. Directors, circa 1966-1996
  - Series 2. General Counsel - Ralph S. Abascal, 1970-1996
    - Agricultural issues; includes notes, correspondence, and other information on California Agrarian Action Project (CAAP) v. UC Regents; also correspondence, notes, and a government report on pesticide use (16 folders), 1980-1983, 1985 (Box 175)
    - Biographical papers; includes periodical features, as well as publications related to the perception of lawyers and the law (4 folders), 1987-1991 (Box 274)
    - Environmental issues; includes documents from his tenure at Hastings as well as various conferences, and legal topics such as: zoning and minorities, national environmental policies issues, pollution, agricultural workers health and safety issues, women and children environmental risks, and toxic dumping; file types include pleadings, notes, trial excerpts, publications, and correspondence (17 folders), circa 1990-1995 (Carton 270)
    - Farmworker issues; includes files mostly regarding farmworkers' rights, labor issues, minorities, poverty and housing, banking, and dump locations; includes research, publications, clippings, memos and correspondence, corporate documents of the national legal counsel for the poor(17 folders)., circa 1990-1995 (Carton 271)
    - LSC (Legal Services Corporation) refunding files; includes research, reports, articles, pleadings, correspondence, memos, notes relating to the reauthorization of funding and related CRLA survival issues (24 folders), circa 1978-1985 (Carton 253)
    - LSC (Legal Services Corporation) refunding files; includes research, reports, articles, pleadings, correspondence, memos, notes relating to the reauthorization of funding, related legislation, and CRLA survival issues (27 folders), circa 1978-1985 (Carton 254)
    - LSC (Legal Services Corporation) refunding files; includes research, reports, articles, pleadings, correspondence, memos, notes relating to the reauthorization of funding and related CRLA survival issues (11 folders), circa 1978-1985 (Box 255)
    - LSC (Legal Services Corporation) working files; includes mostly correspondence regarding grant funding between CRLA and: LSC, Center for Law and Social Policy, and other legal agencies; also includes LSC monitoring report (1986), LSC's request for production of documents, and the Project Advisory Group's "Washington Reports" (16 folders), 1976, circa 1980-1990 (Carton 278)
    - LSC (Legal Services Corporation) working files; includes pleadings from cases files against LSC, reports, publications, and opinions regarding LSC, legislative research regarding grant funding, and a report by the Comptroller General (16 folders), circa 1977-1990 (Carton 290)
    - LSC (Legal Services Corporation) working files; includes Martin Holt's report on migrant workers' distribution, their research, and various responses to the 1987 report, as well as LSC's 1990 legislative battles, LSC Reauthorization Act, which includes correspondence, senate bill critiques, memos, clippings, and a draft monitoring report from 1985 (20 folders), circa 1985-1995 (Carton 273)
    - LSC (Legal Services Corporation) working files; includes clippings regarding funding conflict and Abascal's grant proposal conditions files (5 folders), circa 1990 (Box 279)
    - Pesticides; includes files related to pesticides and OSHA guidelines, as well as reproductive rights for women; includes pleadings from the Commission to Defend Reproductive Rights and Comison Femenil Mexicana v. Kizer (State Health Dept.), Chemical Manufacturers Association v. California Health & Welfare Agency, Ixta v. Rinaldi (CA v. OSHA lawsuit), and information on RICO from the California Bar Association, (28 folders), circa 1990-1995 (Carton 272)
    - Mixed case files; includes RSA v. Reagan pleadings, TRLA v. LSC research documents, ULWC (United Legal Workers of California) strike against CRLA working files, and other LSC papers regarding refund of money (5 folders), circa 1985-1995 (Box 275)
    - Mixed files; includes Abascal v. Crocker National Bank; pleadings, correspondence, notes; Robert H. Bork nomination file; loose clippings and articles (13 folders), circa 1987 (Box 168)
    - Mixed files; includes correspondence, memos, reports, pleadings, subject files, research, notes, clippings and articles; Barr v. Catholic Social Services; Kutak-Dodds Prize; material related to mechanization case, including typescript speech (29 folders), circa 1969-1996 (Carton 256)
  - Series 3. Litigation Directors, 1973-1996
    This series contains meeting material, conference and training material, administrative files, correspondence, and notes relating to the general function of the litigation directors, directing attorneys, and directing legal secretaries. Also included are records related to specific ligation directors, such as Richard Gonzales and Richard Pearl. Material related to the work of other directing attorneys, especially if it includes extensive case files can also be found in Record Group 5, Series 2. Litigation.
    - Advanced Litigation Directors conference materials (1 folder) 1984 (Half-box 378)
    - Directing Attorneys litigation meetings; includes correspondence, meeting minutes, memos, and lists relating to directing attorneys and litigation activities (15 folders), 1976-77, 1979-81, 1983-84 (Carton 126)
    - Directing Attorney/Directing Legal Secretary meeting material (4 folders), 1990-1993 (Box 376)
    - Directing Attorney Orientation; includes training materials related to special topics, including funding, supervision, case selection and management, priorities and task forces (18 folders), circa 1978-1979 (Box 52)
    - Richard Gonzales files; includes correspondence, chronological files, administrative and subject files (33 folders), 1973-1976 (Carton 59)
    - Richard Pearl files; includes correspondence, memos, notes, meeting minutes, and other materials related to Pearl's term as Director of Litigation; subjects include hiring employees and interns, the Priorities Conference, and the Job Creation Task Force (16 folders), 1977-1978 (Carton 124)
    - Richard Pearl files; includes correspondence, minutes, reports, and articles related to Pearl's activities in Directing Attorneys' meetings and the farm labor, education, housing, and job creation task forces (15 folders), 1977-1978 (Carton 125)
- Record Group 3. Administrative and Financial files, circa 1966-1994
  This record group contains correspondence, memos, reports, budget information, meeting material, program evaluations, office manuals, and miscellaneous office files relating to the daily administrative and financial operations of CRLA's central office, as well as some of the regional branch offices. Other materials of interest include contracts and other records related to community and legal workers unions, particularly the United Legal Workers of California (ULWC). Also included are files compiled by Barbara Rasmussen, Special Assistant to the Executive Director and later Community Relations Coordinator.
  - Series 1. General Administrative and Financial Records
    - Accrual reports; also includes budget deficit information, 1986 (Box 14)
    - Administrative records; includes evaluations, budgets, correspondence, memos, reports, and training materials; subjects include evaluations of branch offices and merger of CRLA with regional legal aid offices (22 folders), 1976-1982 (Carton 92)
    - Administrative records; includes correspondence, memos, and other material relating to central administration, alternate structure committee, food law, general counsel, library, litigation unit, migrant unit, reclamation unit, regional counsel, senior citizens, and CRLA branch offices (26 folders), 1977-1982 (Carton 116)
    - Administrative records; includes chronological files and LSC monitoring material related to the CRLA's internal operations (10 folders), 1985-1986 (Box 94)
    - Administrative records; includes CRLA by-laws, regional office assessments, grievance procedure, and basic unit litigation report from 1988 (4 folders), circa 1988 (Box 296)
    - Administrative records; includes job announcements, seniority lists, and worksheets (5 folders), 1982-1990 (Box 118)
    - Administrative records; includes LSC monitoring material related to the CRLA's internal operations PBI (private bar involvement) files, regional counsel applicants, and narrative reports (13 folders), circa 1983-1987 (Box 293)
    - Administrative records; includes manuals, contact lists, correspondence, notes, and memos related to CRLA's work with local legal aid societies, responsibilities of the office administrator and assistant, and the day-to-day workings of the central CRLA office (16 folders), 1973-1977 (Box 63)
    - Administrative records; includes correspondence, memos, contracts, insurance policies, and statistical reports related to the day-to-day functions of the CRLA central office (24 folders), 1979-1986 (Carton 147)
    - Administrative records; includes correspondence, memos, reports, and audits related to the day-to-day functions of the CRLA central office (8 folders), 1979-1985 (Box 148)
    - Administrative records; includes correspondence, memos, meeting minutes, notes, job descriptions, salary scales, personnel manuals, and other material (25 folders), 1978-1986 (Carton 151)
    - Administrative records; includes correspondence, memos, policies, seniority lists, and personnel manuals; topics include the education and health task forces, ULWC policies and procedures, and unemployment compensation (23 folders), 1976-1986 (Box 152)
    - Administrative records; includes memos, correspondence, leases, manuals, and other material relating to the daily functions of the CRLA central office; topics include computer information, job announcements, training, and office procedures (14 folders), 1976-80, 1982-86, 1989 (Box 203)
    - Administrative and financial records; includes correspondence, evaluations, memos, budgets, and reports relating to employment matters (job descriptions, employee classifications and salary, evaluation and training, seniority lists), caseload management, CRLA history, alternative structure committee, finances, equipment disposal, budget, and conferences attended by CRLA staff (27 folders), 1970-1990 (Carton 117)
    - Administrative and financial records; includes memos, correspondence, reports, and other material related to staff finance and budget committee, smoking policy, two-bar rule waivers, summer work study interns, transcript reimbursement funds, the Reginald Heber Smith Fellowship Program, and telephone delivery (15 folders), 1980-1984 (Carton 127)
    - Administrative and financial records; includes memos, correspondence, training material, and manuals relating to the daily functions of the CRLA central office; topics include the budget, work study programs, and eathquake safety (20 folders), 1982-1988 (Carton 178)
    - Administrative and financial records; includes memos, budgets, correspondence, manuals, statistics, forms, and other materials relating to the daily functions of the CRLA central office; topics include budgets, field visits, operations, personnel, and office management (18 folders), 1978-1979, 1982-1985 (Carton 209)
    - Administrative and financial records; includes fiscal reports, office memos, forms, and statistical reports related to the CRLA's internal operations; also includes CRLA Operations Manual (1973) and new attorney training and orientation material (1973-1974) (33 folders), 1971-1974 (Carton 91)
    - Administrative and financial records; includes budgets, memos, correspondence, reports, complaints, training, polls, and other information relating to the daily functions of the CRLA central office; topics include budget deficits, training, social security, retrenchment, and pest control (21 folders), 1971-1981, 1985-88 (Carton 264)
    - Administrative and financial records; includes audits, memos, correspondence, reports, training information, and other materials relating to the daily functions of the CRLA central office (17 folders), 1985-1988 (Box 343)
    - Attorney fees; includes notes, memos, reports, timesheets (7 folders), 1984-1986 (Box 41)
    - Financial reports (basic and migrant); includes memos, notes, 1982-1986 (Carton 13)
    - Financial reports (basic and migrant); includes memos, notes, budget planning, deficit information, LSC refunding applications, library unit budget (12 folders), 1984-1987 (Box 40)
  - Series 2. Chronological Office Files
    - Chronological office files; includes memos, correspondence, and other material related to the daily functions of the CRLA central office (42 folders), 1981-1984 (Carton 153)
    - Chronological office files; includes memos, correspondence, and other material related to the daily functions of the CRLA central office, as well as correspondence from administrators and accountants (8 folders), 1981, 1984-85 (Box 154)
    - Chronological office files; includes correspondence, memos, contracts, and applications relating to the day-to-day functions of the CRLA central office (19 folders), 1985-1986 (Box 146)
    - Chronological office files; includes memos, correspondence, and other material related to the daily functions of the CRLA central office (9 folders), 1990 (Carton 177)
  - Series 3. Evaluation Files
    - Employee evaluations and California Community Workers Union negotiations; includes master forms, memos, notes, and contracts (18 folders), 1977-79, 1981-83 (Carton 233)
    - Evaluation materials; forms and training materials for evaluating attorneys, staff, cases, and programs (7 folders), circa 1977-1978 (Box 53)
    - Office evaluation files; includes Madera office material, case summary reports, memos; also central office evaluation report (2 folders), circa 1971-1978 (Box 386)
      Restricted Material
      Closed until 2053
  - Series 4. Meetings
    - Executive meetings; includes agendas, memos, notes, reports; also Appeals Committee, Nominating Committee, and miscellaneous meeting material (14 folders), 1977-1980 (Box 57)
    - Finance Committee meetings; includes agendas, memos, notes, reports (12 folders), 1978-1980 (Box 56)
  - Series 5. Barbara Rasmussen Files
    - Barbara Rasmussen subject files; includes correspondence, memos, reports, news articles, testimony, and other materials related to CRLA activities (44 folders), 1966-1972 (Carton 111)
    - Barbara Rasmussen subject files; includes correspondence, memos, reports, news articles, testimony, and other materials related to CRLA activities (26 folders), 1966-1972 (Carton 101)
  - Series 6. Regional Offices
    - El Centro files; includes clippings, notes, memos, contracts, miscellaneous files (10 folders), 1988-1998 (Box 375)
    - Stanislaus Legal Aid; includes materials related to the day-to-day running of the Stanislaus Legal Aid office, such as invoices, tax returns, receipts, newsletters, correspondence, memos, grant applications, and other material (50 folders), 1974-1977 (Carton 143)
    - Stanislaus Legal Aid; includes materials related to the day-to-day running of the Stanislaus Legal Aid office, such as invoices, receipts, and financial statements (42 folders), 1974-1977 (Carton 145)
  - Series 7. United Legal Workers of California (ULWC)
    - United Legal Workers of California (ULWC) contracts; includes contract negotiations and correspondence, contract proposals, notes, budget worksheets, drafts, union bargaining materials (10 folders), 1980-1982 (Box 44)
    - United Legal Workers of California (ULWC) and California Community Workers Union negotiations; includes memoranda, correspondence, notes, and contracts, as well as news clippings and other material related to the ULWC strike in 1978 (17 folders), 1977-78, 1980, 1982-83 (Carton 234)
  - Series 8. Miscellaneous Material
    - Miscellaneous material; notes, memos, clippings, pleadings (21 folders), circa 1983-1989 (Carton 373)
    - Miscellaneous material; includes memos regarding training, standards, and performance monitoring; also publication relating to Latino issues (2 folders), 1994 (Box 374)
- Record Group 4. Communication and Development files, circa 1966-1996
  This record group contains correspondence, memos, press releases, news clippings, reports, articles and other materials related to CRLA's efforts to communicate their goals and accomplishments to the general public, and to monitor the public’s perception of CRLA. It also includes grant applications, fund-raising files, and outreach event information, documenting CRLA's strategies for securing support for the organization. Of particular interest are the many letters of support for CRLA sent in response to Reagan's 1970 veto of CRLA funding. This series also contains material related to the establishment of the California Rural Legal Assistance Foundation (CRLAF) and its effort to secure funding for CRLA activities outside the federal government.
  - Series 1. CRLA Foundation (CRLAF)
    - CRLA Foundation (CRLAF) articles of incorporation and bylaws (1 folder), 1981 (Half-box 379)
    - CRLA Foundation (CRLAF); includes billing and contract information for grants administered by the CRLA Foundation (22 folders), 1982-1987 (Carton 179)
    - CRLA Foundation (CRLAF); includes memoranda, correspondence, and contracts related to the daily functions of the CRLAF; also includes records related to the Rural Justice Foundation, a precursor to the CRLAF (26 folders), 1978-1980, 1986, 1991 (Carton 237)
    - CRLA Foundation (CRLAF); includes memoranda, correspondence, and other material related to the daily functions of the CRLAF (3 folders), 1983-84 (Box 238)
  - Series 2. Fundraising and Grant Files
    - Fundraising and publicity materials; includes newsclippings, memos, correspondence, budgets, notes, and CRLA publications on a range of topics including CRLAF board meetings, fundraising, grants, support and recognition events, and requests for publications (16 folders), 1966, 1981-83, 1985-86, 1988-1990 (Carton 265)
    - Grant materials; includes proposals, correspondence, budgets, reports, and other material related to grants from foundations such as the Episcopal Coalition for Human Needs, the Poverello Fund, and the Walter S. Johnson Foundation (66 folders), 1982-1989 (Carton 137)
    - Grant materials; includes proposals, correspondence, budgets, reports, and other material related to grants from foundations such as the MacArthur Foundation and National Rural Fellows (36 folders), 1982-1989 (Box 138)
    - Grant materials; includes proposals, correspondence, budgets, reports, and other material related to grants from the Needmor Fund and Northern California Grantmakers (10 folders), 1984 (Box 139)
    - Miscellaneous material; includes clippings; fund raising conference; San Joaquin Valley healthcare report (3 folders), circa 1990-1996 (Half-box 381)
  - Series 3. News Clippings
    - News clippings; mostly related to California Welfare reform and Reagan (11 folders), 1970-1971 (Box 36)
    - News clippings; includes clippings from California papers containing mention of the CRLA and its work (13 folders), 1971-1972 (Carton 77)
    - News clippings; mostly related to California Welfare reform (42 folders), 1971-1975 (Carton 17)
    - News clippings; photocopies of news clippings about to CRLA activities and related topics (6 folders), circa 1979-1981 (Box 26)
    - News clippings; photocopies of news clippings relating to legal services compiled by the Legal Services Corporation (LSC) (21 folders), circa 1981-1982 (Carton 18)
    - News clippings; photocopies of news clippings relating to legal services compiled by the Legal Services Corporation (LSC) (6 folders), circa 1981-1982 (Box 19)
    - News clippings; photocopies of news clippings about CRLA activities and related topics (12 folders), circa 1982 (Box 27)
    - News clippings, 1976, 1985 (Carton 170, Folders 10-13)
    - News clippings and press releases; includes press releases issued by CRLA as well as clippings of articles mentioning CRLA (7 folders), 1967-1970 (Box 65)
    - News clippings and summaries; photocopies of news clippings about to CRLA activities and related topics; includes articles and reports ( 4 folders), circa 1968-1980 (Box 28)
    - News clippings; related to CRLA activities and priority areas (12 folders), 1979-1980 (Box 311)
    - News clippings; related to CRLA activities and priority areas (16 folders), 1983-1987 (Carton 167)
  - Series 4. Publications
    - Publications; includes Poverty and Social Reform: OEO, Legal Services and the Case of California Rural Legal Assistance (Don R. Broyles) (2 folders) (Half-box 380)
    - Publications; includes drafts and offprints of “California Rural Legal Assistance (CRLA): Survival of a Poverty Law Practice” by Michael Bennett and Cruz Reynoso, as well as related correspondence; offprint of Political Interference with Publicly Funded Lawyers: The CRLA Controversy and the Future of Legal Services" by Jerome B. Falk, Jr. and Stuart R. Pollak; CRLA publication Rural California: Hope Amidst Poverty; and publications from other organizations that relate to CRLA work (8 folders)., 1971-1973 (Box 64)
    - Publications; includes articles written by CRLA staff and discussion about a CRLA newsletter, 1981, 1985-86 (Carton 170, Folders 6-9)
    - Publications from other organizations, 1974-1977 (Carton 170, Folders 1-5)
  - Series 5. Support Letters (Reagan Veto)
    - Support letters (Reagan veto); includes refunding support letters from legal service organizations, law schools, politicians, health, welfare, and labor organizations, religious groups, attorneys, judiciary, and others, mostly to Governor Reagan, President Nixon, and OEO Directors, Donald Rumsfeld and Frank Carlucci; also communication with CRLA regarding support efforts (34 folders), circa 1967-1971 (Carton 23)
    - Support letters (Reagan veto); includes refunding support letters from legal service organizations, law schools, politicians, health, welfare, and labor organizations, religious groups, attorneys, judiciary, and others, mostly to Governor Reagan, President Nixon, and OEO Directors, Donald Rumsfeld and Frank Carlucci; also communication with CRLA regarding support efforts (36 folders), circa 1970-1971 (Carton 24)
    - Support letters (Reagan veto); includes refunding support letters from legal service organizations, law schools, politicians, health, welfare, and labor organizations, religious groups, attorneys, judiciary, and others, mostly to Governor Reagan, President Nixon, and OEO Directors, Donald Rumsfeld and Frank Carlucci; also communication with CRLA regarding support efforts (9 folders), circa 1970-1971 (Box 25)
- Record Group 5. Advocacy, circa 1967-1998
  This record group contains material related to CRLA's legal, community, and policy advocacy work. CRLA legal staff not only represented clients in court, but also advocated before state commissions such as the utilities board to institute policies that would aid the poor and those for whom English was not their first language. The record group is divided into three series. The first series contains working files from CRLA attorneys Stephen Rosenbaum and Tony White. The Legislation series contains drafts and copies of California Senate and Assembly Bills relevant to CRLA priority areas, as well as related correspondence and notes. The Litigation Series contains pleadings, research and discovery files, case notes, memos, and correspondence from legal cases, either argued by CRLA attorneys or of interest to CRLA. Sample cases include California Agrarian Action Project (CAAP) v. University of California Regents, Furukawa Farms v. CRLA, and United Farm Workers (UFW) v. Immigration and Naturalization Services (INS).